<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<pretext>
<docinfo>
  <latex-image-preamble>
    \usepackage{tikz}
  </latex-image-preamble>
  <macros>
    \newcommand{\into}{\hookrightarrow}
    \newcommand{\onto}{\twoheadrightarrow}
  </macros>
</docinfo>

<book xml:id="IntroCGGT">
  <title>An introduction to combinatorial and geometric group
    theory</title>
    <author>Nicholas Touikan</author>
    <introduction xml:id="chap_intro"><title>Introduction</title>
    <p>
      Because the field of geometric group theory is relatively new,
      sounds cool, is cool, and is accessible, it is, in 2020, very
      active and evolving. This also means that geometric group
      theory means different things to different people.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Drutu and Kapovich's imposing 2018 monograph
      <i>Geometric Group Theory</i> arguably gives the most
      comprehensive overview of the field, but it omits certain
      important topics such as CAT(0) cube complexes or
      <m>\mathrm{Out}(F_n)</m> and the spaces it acts on, which are
      touched on in Volume 21 of the IAS/Park City Mathematics
      series titled <i>Geometric Group Theory</i>. And even these do
      not cover some of the author's favourite topics.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      The breadth of field forces us to limit our scope. Lie groups,
      for example, are certainly interesting as groups, are very
      geometrical, and would certainly have their place in a course
      in geometric group theory. But, Dynkin diagrams
      notwithstanding, drawings are not a major tool for dealing
      with Lie groups.
    </p>
      
    <p>
      This course will be a self-contained introduction to the art of
      working with infinite discrete groups by drawing pictures. We
      will start with a rigourous exploration of the <m>F_n</m>, the
      free group on <m>n</m> generators and touch on the clasical
      subject of combinatorial group theory, which is the study of
      groups given by generators and relations. Our driving question
      will be: <i>Which calculations can we perform, or which
      algorithmic problems can we solve, in a group given by a certain
      presentation?</i>
    </p>
    <p>
      Our approach to this will be geometrical: group presentations
      enable us to draw Van Kampen diagrams and we will see that in
      the presence of (combinatorial) negative curvature, many
      algorithmic problems become tractable.
    </p>
    
    <p>Modified August 17, 2020</p>

    </introduction>

    <chapter><title>Free groups and presentations</title>
    <section xml:id="Lecture_1"><title>Lecture 1: Reduced words</title>
    <p>Foo</p>
    Write group axioms define a structure 
    </section>
    </chapter>
    
      <!--introduction>
	<p>
	  Since the dawn of time blablabla.
	</p>
	<p>
	  This is a short sentence. <m> R \onto S</m> <m>2+2</m>
	</p>
    
      </introduction-->
</book>
</pretext>

<!-->      
      <section xml:id="section-1">
	<title>Section 1</title>
	<p> Muhaha! </p>
	<image source="images/cat.jpg"/>
      </section>


      <section xml:id="sec-2">
	<title> Whaaat?</title>
	<p> Here is some math <m>2+2=4</m> and moar math
	<me>\sum_{i=1}^\infty a_i, a_i \in \mathbb R </me></p>
	<ol>
	  <li> Here'a thing</li>
	  <li> here's another </li>
	</ol>

	<figure>
	  <caption>Tikz test</caption>
	<image width="50%" xml:id="tikztext">
	  <latex-image>
	    \begin{tikzpicture}
	    \node (a) at (0,0) {$\alpha$};
	    \node (b) at (2,0) {$\gamma$};
	    \end{tikzpicture}
	  </latex-image>
	  
	</image>
	</figure>
      </section>
</book>
    
  </pretext>
<!-->
